Hill, A. mss., 1886-2004 LMC 2666
Lilly Library
Hill, A. mss.
1886-2004
Lilly Library
Hill, Anne (Gathorne-Hardy), 1911-2006
LMC 2666
12 Boxes
The Hill, A. mss., ca. 1886-2004, consist of correspondence, journal fragments, legal and financial documents, clippings, photos, and account books of Lady Anne Hill (1911–2006), author, public figure, and wife of prominent bookseller G. Heywood Hill.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Lady Anne Gathorne-Hardy (October 12, 1911-October 22, 2006) was born in 1911, the only daughter of the third Earl of Cranbrook and his wife, Dorothy. Her four older brothers were John (Jock) Gathorne-Hardy (1900-1974), Edward (Eddie) Gathorne-Hardy, Robert (Bob) Gathorne-Hardy, and Antony Gathorne-Hardy. The family was ennobled in the 1870's after Anne's great grandfather served in Disraeli's cabinet. She was originally engaged to James Lees-Milne, but the two parted amicably. She was an original employee of Heywood Hill book shop, named for its owner, who was a cousin of Anne's sister-in-law. Anne married Heywood in 1938; their marriage spanned nearly fifty years until Heywood's death of Parkinson's disease in 1986. They had two daughters, Harriet Frazer (previously Harriet Behrens) and Rabea (formerly Lucy) Redpath.
Lady Anne was interested in family history and relations, keeping detailed records of her ancestors' lineage dating back centuries. She was also particularly interested in Edward Trelawny, a friend of Lord Byron's, and wrote and published scholarly pamphlets and books on him, most notably Trelawny's Strange Relations (1956). Together with Heywood, she also published a volume of their wartime correspondence (during which time Heywood served in the military while Anne ran the shop) entitled A Bookseller's War.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series: I. Heywood Hill Bookstore, II. Lady Anne Hill (includes A. Correspondence, B. Photos, C. Legal & Financial, D. Personal, E. Jane Gathorne-Hardy, F. Eddie Gathorne-Hardy, G. Writings), III. Miscellaneous.
Scope and Content Note
"Heywood Hill Bookstore" "Correspondence" subseries includes letters about the shop between Lady Anne, Heywood Hill, and various other correspondents, including Mollie and Handasyde Buchanan (the latter jouned the shop in 1945 and managed the shop 1965-1974), John Saumarez-Smith (joined in 1965 and became managing director after Handasyde's departure, until 2008). Most correspondence related to Nancy Mitford (renowned 20th century author and socialite, who worked in the shop 1942-1945) can also be found here.
Much of the "Correspondence" subseries of "Lady Anne Hill" was organized to varying degrees by Lady Anne herself. As she organized mainly chronologically and thematically (e.g. "Cyprus trip 1968"), I chose to leave many non-correspondence material (such as programs, photos, catalogs, press clippings, etc.) in Lady Anne's original arrangement as they often cohere thematically or lend each other context. Notable correspondents that can be found in this series include author Frances Partridge and James Lees-Milne.
Due to the organizational system used in correspondence, a number of photos are in that subseries. Any photos without clear organizational logic, dates, or seeming relevance to the materials near which they were originally located were placed in the "Photos" subseries.
The "Personal" subseries to "Lady Anne Hill" contains many of the materials that were less organized/more loosely organized by Lady Anne. Some overlap between the folders can be found throughout the collection but especially in this subseries due to multiple processors who processed roughly half the collection.
"Jane Gathorne-Hardy" includes correspondence (some with Anne) as well as personal papers, documents, and photos of Lady Anne's aunt, Jane Ethel Gathorne-Hardy (Sept. 26, 1872-1943). According to Anne's papers, she seems to have been a suffragette and world traveler (she lived in France and Peruvian ID documents can be found under "Personal").
"Eddie Gathorne-Hardy" includes correspondence with and papers related to or belonging to Lady Anne's brother Eddie, including his correspondence with English travel writer Peter Mayne (1908-1979).
"Writings" includes Lady Anne's scholarship on Edward Trelawny, including correspondence and writings related to Trelawny's 1831 memoir, Adventures of a Younger Son (Anne contacted publishing houses to encourage them to publish a new edition in the hopes of writing the introduction) as well as Lady Anne's own book, Trelawny's Strange Relations, centered on his mother and sisters. This subseries also includes Anne and Heywood's work of compiling their wartime letters into what would become A Bookseller's War (1997), as well as some work related to a memoir. Lady Anne's "Nannies," written for a collection her nephew, Jonny Gathorne-Hardy, was working on.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 2007
Related Materials
See Hill, H. mss. and Gathorne-Hardy, J. mss., also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Booksellers and bookselling; Hill, Anne, 1911-2006; Hill, Heywood, 1906-1986; G. Heywood Hill, Ltd; Trelawny, Edward John, 1792-1881 -- Biography
- Heywood Hill Bookstore (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - 1936-1940 (Box 1)
    - Nancy Mitford 1942-1951 (Box 1)
    - Extracts & Nancy Mitford 1943-1944 (Box 1)
    - 1944-1945 (Box 1)
    - 1943-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1963 (Box 1)
    - 1964 (Box 1)
    - 1965 (Box 1)
    - Robin McDouall's Party for Heywood 1966 (Box 1)
    - 1963-1973 In Praise of Heywood (Box 1)
    - 1966-1977 (Box 1)
    - John Saumarez-Smith Letters 1966-1988 (Box 1)
    - 1986 (Box 1)
    - 1986-1990 (Box 1)
    - Resale of Shop 1991 (Box 1)
  - Legal & Financial
    - 1936 (Box 1)
    - Profit & Loss 1937-1947 (Box 1)
    - Accounts Outstanding 1939 (Box 1)
    - Profit & Loss 1948-1963 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper & Magazine 1931-1988 (Box 1)
  - Catalogs 1940-1986 (Box 1)
  - Anne's Notes (Box 1)
- Lady Anne Hill
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence Inventory (Box 1)
    - Undated, Folder 1 (Box 1)
    - Undated, Folder 2 (Box 2)
    - Pre-1900 (Box 2)
    - 1900-1902 (Box 2)
    - Heywood Hill 1914-1938 (Box 2)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes a 1932 journal, Heywood's school report card. Some are undated or loosely dated by Anne.
    - 1920-1923 (Box 2)
    - Frances Partridge 1922-1997 (Box 2)
      Some letters to/from Partridge were missed in Anne Hill's original arrangement; some have been moved here but others might still exist in other correspondence files.
    - 1927-1929 (Box 2)
    - Letters from Finishing School, 1929 (Box 2)
    - Jan. 1, 1932-Dec. 31, 1932 (Box 2)
    - 1933-1937 (Box 2)
    - Autumn 1937-Sept. 1938 (Box 2)
    - Sept. 18, 1938-Jan. 11, 1939 (Box 2)
    - 1939 (Box 2)
    - Jan. 1939-Aug. 1940 (Box 2)
    - 1940-1942 (Box 2)
    - Anne and Heywood Hill, Dec. 1942-May 19423, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1943 (Box 2)
    - 1944 (Box 2)
    - 1945 (Box 2)
    - 1947 (Box 2)
    - Jan. 1, 1948-Dec. 31, 1948 (Box 2)
    - 1949 (Box 2)
    - 1950s (no precise year) (Box 2)
    - 1950 (Box 2)
    - 1951 (Box 3)
    - 1952 (Box 3)
    - 1953 (Box 3)
    - 1954 (Box 3)
    - 1955 (Box 3)
    - Gerald Hochschild 1956-1958, (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 3)
    - Jan. 1, 1958-Dec. 31, 1958 (Box 3)
    - 1959 (Box 3)
    - 1960 (Box 3)
    - 1961 (Box 3)
    - 1962 (Box 3)
    - 1963 (Box 3)
    - 1964 (Box 3)
    - 1965 (Box 4)
    - 1966 (Box 4)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 4)
    - Jan.-June 1967 (Box 4)
    - July-Aug. 1967 (Box 4)
    - Sept.-Dec. 1967 (Box 4)
    - 1968, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Cyprus trip 1968 (Box 4)
    - 1969 (Box 4)
    - 1970, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1971, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1972, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - 1973, Folder 1 (Box 4)
    - 1973, Folders 2-4 (Box 5)
    - 1974, (4 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1975, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1976, (4 folders) (Box 5)
    - 1977, (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - 1978, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - 1979, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - 1980, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - 1981, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - 1982, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - 1983, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - 1984, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - 1985, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - 1986, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Heywood's Death 1986, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - 1987 (Box 7)
    - 1988 (Box 8)
    - 1989 (Box 8)
    - 1990 (Box 8)
    - 1991 (Box 8)
    - 1992 (Box 8)
    - Garrard's Portrait of Anne, 1993 (Box 8)
    - 1993 (Box 8)
    - 1994 (Box 8)
    - 1995 (Box 8)
    - 1996-1999 (Box 8)
    - 2000-2003 (Box 8)
  - Photos (Box 9)
    - 1886-2000 (Box 9)
    - Lucy/Rabea, Undated (Box 9)
    - Undated (Box 9)
    - Trelawny (Box 9)
    - Robert Gathorne-Hardy's Estate (Box 9)
  - Legal & Financial
    - Correspondence
      - Snape & Orchard Cottage 1965 (Box 9)
      - 1938-1995 (Box 9)
    - Low Farm (Property) (Box 9)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 9)
    - 1965-1968 (Box 9)
    - Lucy/Rabea's Trust, 1966-1976 (Box 9)
    - 1969-1972 (Box 9)
    - 1973-1976 (Box 9)
    - Death of Robert Gathorne-Hardy
      - General 1973-1976 (Box 9)
      - Sale of Art 1973-1976 (Box 9)
      - Estate 1973-1975 (Box 9)
    - 1976 (Box 9)
    - 1977 (Box 9)
    - 1978 (Box 9)
    - 1979 (Box 9)
    - 1980 (Box 9)
    - 1981 (Box 9)
    - 1982 (Box 9)
    - 1983 (Box 9)
    - 1984 (Box 9)
    - 1985 (Box 9)
    - 1986 (Box 9)
    - 1987 (Box 9)
    - 1998 (Box 9)
  - Personal
    - Hill Family Archive
      - Correspondence
        - 1981-1982 (Box 9)
        - 1983-1984 (Box 9)
          Mostly with Colin Franklin and Bill Cagle at the Lilly.
        - 1989 (Box 9)
        - Lilly Library 1993-1994 (Box 9)
      - Jonny Gathorne-Hardy's Prospectus (Box 9)
      - Organizational Notes 1900-2008 (Box 10)
      - Index 1980-1989 (Box 10)
      - Anne's Notes (Box 10)
        Includes an index of dates of major life events written by Anne to help with dating undated letters.
    - Family History
      - Gathorne-Hardy (Box 10)
      - Hill and Gathorne-Hardy (Box 10)
    - Household Management 1907-1957 (Box 10)
    - Hand-Copied Poems 1929 (Box 10)
    - Anne's Notes About Her Children 1948-1956 (Box 10)
    - 1931-1945 (Box 10)
    - Printed Materials (Box 10)
    - Frances Partridge 1942-1967 (Box 10)
      An incomplete summary composed by Lady Anne of Partridge's letters.
    - Photocopies, Magazine Articles, Newspaper Clippings 1981-1990 (Box 10)
    - Newsclippings (Box 10)
    - Newspaper Dec. 9, 1961 (Box 10)
    - Clippings 1965-1982 (Box 10)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1985-2002 (Box 10)
    - Misc. Invitations & Announcements (Box 10)
    - Wedding 1937-1938 (Box 10)
    - Misc. Undated (Box 10)
    - Journal
      - 1955-1958 (Box 10)
      - 1959-1960 (Box 10)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 10)
      - 1961-1963 (Box 10)
      - Day Planners 1962-1977 (Box 10)
      - 1966-1968 (Box 10)
      - Journal 2001 (Box 11)
      - Notebook, undated (Box 11)
      - Misc. spiral notebooks, undated (Box 11)
    - Drawings/Prints (Box 11)
    - Programs 1973-1995 (Box 11)
    - Dreams & Hallucinations 1936-1989 (Box 11)
    - 1970-1979 (Box 11)
    - Friends 1978-1991, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Family (Box 11)
    - Abstract from "The History of Lynn B. William Richards M.A., 1892" (Box 11)
    - Postcards, Cards & Photos (Box 11)
    - Blank Postcards (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous & Undated (Box 11)
  - Jane Gathorne-Hardy
    - Correspondence
      - 1936-1940, (2 folders) (Box 11)
      - With Anne 1939-1940 (Box 11)
    - Personal
      - Personal (Box 11)
    - Legal & Financial
      - Legal & Financial (Box 11)
    - Photos
      - Photos, undated (Box 11)
  - Eddie Gathorne-Hardy
    - Correspondence
      - 1927-1978, (2 folders) (Box 11)
      - Peter Mayne 1975-1979 (Box 12)
      - Eddie's Death 1978 (Box 12)
    - Writings
      - Writings (Box 12)
    - Legal/Financial/Medical
      - Legal/Financial/Medical 1968-1978 (Box 12)
    - Eddiana
      - 1978-2004, (3 folders) (Box 12)
  - Writings
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
    - Juvenalia (Box 12)
    - Memoir
      - Notes (Box 12)
      - Hawkins and Lees-Milne Diary Excerpts (Box 12)
      - Anne's Summary of Diaries 1921-1992 (Box 12)
      - Memoirs (Box 12)
    - Edward Trelawny
      - Edward Trelawny's Adventures of a Younger Son
        - Correspondence re:Adventures of a Younger Son (Box 12)
      - Lady Anne Hill's Trelawny's Strange Relations
        - Reviews of Trelawny's Strange Relations (Box 12)
        - Trelawny's Strange Relations (Box 12)
      - Edward Trelawny, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - A Bookseller's War
      - Manuscript of A Bookseller's War (Box 12)
      - Correspondence re: A Bookseller's War (Box 12)
      - Notes Related to A Bookseller's War (Box 12)
    - "Nannies"
      - "Nannies" 1970 (Box 12)
    - "Ruth at Kelburn"
      - "Ruth at Kelburn" (Box 12)
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous (Box 12)